Guide to the Dante Gabriel Rossetti Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dante Gabriel Rossetti collection
1840-1881
GEN MSS 268
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Letters by Rossetti to various parties, including Sir Frederic Burton and Frederic James Shields, along with one letter from Charles Augustus Howell to Rossetti. One manuscript by Rossetti: "At Wellington's Funeral. 18th November 1852," an autograph receipt, and a deck of playing cards painted by Rossetti at the age of 12.
Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Dante Gabriel Rossetti, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to June 1997 have been organized into three series. Series I, Correspondence, principally contains items written by Rossetti, with one letter written to Rossetti by Charles Augustus Howell. The single item in Series II, Writings, is a manuscript poem. The Other Materials in Series III consist of an autograph receipt and a set of playing cards painted by Rossetti at the age of 12.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Painters -- England; Playing cards; Burton, Frederic William, 1816-1900; Howell, Charles Augustus, 1840?-1890; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Shields, Frederic, 1833-1911
- I. Correspondence
  - HOWELL, CHARLES AUGUSTUS
    - ALS to Dante Gabriel Rossetti, London, 1875 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ROSSETTI, DANTE GABRIEL
    - ALS to William Cox Bennett, London, [1851 Jan 8?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Purchase, 1954
    - ALS to Mr. Blunt, 1872 Feb 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Gift, 1942
    - 1 AL & 1 ALS to Sir Frederic Burton, [London?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Purchase, 1957
    - Autograph draft of a telegram to Hall Caine, [after 1880] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Rossetti's name has been clipped from the manuscript. Purchase, 1956
    - ALS to Ernest Gambart, Chelsea, 1865 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Purchase, 1956
    - ALS to Alexander Gilchrist, [1861 Jul 10] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Gift, 1939
    - ALS to Thomas Hake, London, n.y. Wednesday (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Purchase, 1958
    - ALS to Francis Albert Marshall, Hawkhurst, 1870 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Removed from his Poems, London, 1870, Ip.R735.870P.
      Gift, 1952
    - ALS to his mother Frances Mary Lavinia Polidori Rossetti, 1879 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      From the library of Bishop Charles A. Clough, Yale 1926. Gift.
    - 61 ALS to Frederic James Shields, 1869-81 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      A complete list accompanies the manuscripts. Purchase, 1956
    - ALS to Henry Virtue Tebbs, Chelsea, [c. 1865] Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to Henry Wallis, Chelsea, [1865] Monday (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Paper is watermarked "1865". Purchase, 1975
    - ALS to [Theodore] Watts[-Dunton], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Removed fromD. G. Rossetti's Dennis Shand [1869], Ip.R735.869s
      Gift, 1950
    - ALS to Thomas Woolner, London, 1853 Apr (Box 1, Folder 16)
- II. Manuscripts, n.d.
  - "At Wellington's Funeral, 18th November 1852", AMS, with notes concerning the same by W. M. Rossetti, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Gift, 1964
- III. Other Materials, 1876 Mar 21
  - Autograph receipt in his hand to Clarence E. Fry for payment on account of a painting, 1876 Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 52 hand painted playing cards, 1840 Dec (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    Accompanied by letters attesting to the provenance of the cards: William Michael Rossetti to Mrs. Belcher, 1895 Jun 24, and C. J. Belcher to Sotheby & Co., 1927 Dec 5
    Purchase, 1969